"Why Does Ozempic Stop Working for Weight Loss
and What Happens When You Quit?"
People may not understand
the potential limitations
of the new class of Ozempic-like
anti-obesity medications,
especially given the wide hype
these drugs are receiving.
For example, the drugs
don’t work for everybody,
and even when they do,
weight loss stalls out
after a year.
The drug insert included
in every package
of the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss
shows these graphs.
Here’s weight loss
on high-dose semaglutide,
also known as Ozempic,
and sold as Wegovy,
versus placebo.
As you can see,
after about a year,
weight loss stops,
even if you keep injecting
yourself with the drug.
Is it because you’ve plateaued
at a normal weight?
Sadly, no.
They started out obese,
and they ended up obese.
Why does the weight loss
stall out?
Because of what’s presumed
to be a near-exponential rise
in calorie intake,
as the same amount of effort
to cut calories,
whether through willpower,
drugs, or surgery,
is met with
increasing resistance,
as ongoing weight loss activates
your feedback-control circuit,
stimulating your appetite.
So, at first,
the massive GLP-1 activity
triggered by the drugs
lowers your appetite,
but as you lose weight,
your body fights back,
ratcheting your appetite
back up;
so, the same amount
of massive GLP-1 stimulation
causes less
of an appetite suppression.
Within 12 months,
this resistance,
together with the decreased
total energy expenditure
from being lighter,
matches the persistent effort
to cut calories,
and with calories-in
matching calories-out,
weight loss plateaus.
Here it is, graphically.
The same thing happens
whether you’re restricting
calories on a diet,
injecting these fancy new
GLP-1 Ozempic-type drugs,
or going under the knife
for bariatric surgery.
Take high-dose Ozempic.
After the three-month ramp up
in dose,
people are eating nearly
a thousand fewer calories a day.
No wonder they’re losing weight.
But then, the body fights back,
pushing against
the high GLP-1 signaling
and jacking their appetite
back up.
Not all the way back up,
because they’re still injecting
these drugs every week;
so, they still appear to be
eating 400 fewer calories a day
than what they used to.
So, if they’re eating less,
why aren’t they continuing
to lose weight?
Because they’re expending
400 fewer calories
simply because they aren’t
dragging 30 extra pounds
(13 kg) with them
wherever they go.
What happens
if you stop the drug?
In this study, everyone was
started on high-dose Ozempic
for five months
and started to lose weight.
Then, some were randomized
to be unknowingly switched
to placebo injections.
Those who continued
taking the drug,
continued to lose weight,
until the plateau.
Whereas, those who switched
to placebo
started to regain all the weight
they had lost.
It’s the same with tirzepatide,
sold as Zepbound.
As soon as people
stop taking the drug,
the weight starts coming back,
and any benefits
that had been achieved
start to evaporate.
Check it out:
here you can see what happens
when people stop
taking the drug
after being on it
for more than a year.
The pounds pile back on,
two thirds regained
within a year,
and here are some
of the evaporating benefits.
Blood pressure came down
with the weight loss,
but then climbed right back up
as if they never even took
the drug in the first place,
and inflammation
and blood sugars
start creeping back up too.
So, not only
does weight loss stop
as soon as you go off the drug,
but the weight you had lost
before comes back.
So, like in this study,
you may have started out obese,
and ended up obese,
and to maintain your
less-but-still-obese status,
you have to keep
taking these drugs,
presumably every day or week
for the rest of your life.
So, these are forever drugs,
the golden goose
for Big Pharma,
drugs for lifestyle diseases
that you may have
to take lifelong,
since you aren’t treating
the underlying cause,
a fattening diet.